A Guide to the Nourse Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #3490-c
Nourse Family Papers 1768-1904
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
3490-c
16 items
Thomas J. C. Williams
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This accession was given to the Library by Mr. Thomas J.C. Williams of Alexandria, Virginia on July 14, 1983.
Scope and Content
This accession consists of 16 items, 1768-1904, papers of Joseph Nourse, James Nourse, and Charles J. Nourse. Included in the collection are: bound journals, diaries, account books, and commonplace books of Joseph Nourse(1754-1841), and one memorandum book of James Nourse; two English indentures, 1805, concerning the settlement of an estate; six letters (electrostatic copies) to Charles J. Nourse from Henry Clay, John Adams, and John Quincy Adams; and a copy of a 1724 Northern Neck land grant.
Item Listing
- LETTERS
  - Invitation to dine from "The President of the United States and Mrs. Adams" to Mr. and Mrs. Nourse, 1800 Jan. 1; Printed note (electrostatic copy )
  - J[ohn] Q[uincy] Adams to Major C.J. Nourse, Department of War, regarding courts-martial of Captain Boardman and Lieutenant E.K. Smith and J.S. Austin, 1828 Aug. 26; ALS(electrostatic copy )
  - Poem, "The Enchantress," by John Quincy Adams, 1843 Jan. 20; AMS(electrostatic copy)
  - H[enry] Clay to J. Nourse recommending U.S. Representative William Jordan Graves for a task., 1843 Nov. 20; ALS(electrostatic copy )
  - C.J. Nourse to C.J. Nourse, Jr., 1904 Dec. 30; ALSS w/ enclosure
  - F.H. Ormink, Military Secretary to C.J. Nourse, 1904 Dec. 28; ALS
  - "Mr. Clay's respects to Maj. Nourse..." re a visit to Philadelphia, n.d.; Printed note(electrostatic copy)
- BOUND VOLUMES
  - Notebook, bearing the name of James Nourse., 1768 Apr. 4-?
    on the verso of the front paper cover, containing notes on Virginia real estate for sale, lists of furniture, supplies, and arguments for emigration
  - Journal, kept by [Joseph Nourse (1754-1891), 1786 Oct. 11 -1790 Jan. 3
    under "three heads: 1. My Office... 2. My Domestic Affairs... 3. Reflections, or Abstracts on reading," kept in New York. Nourse mentions accounts with several Revolutionary War generals.
  - Account book, kept by [Joseph Nourse?], 1789-1806
    chiefly for domestic accounts, including some receipts and notes. Index.
  - Record book, "Register's Office," kept by Joseph Nourse, register [Office of Register of the Treasury created in 1791 (NARS guide)], w/ scrapbook, 1836-1840, containing notes and newspaper clippings re religion tipped in., 1791-1792
  - Commonplace book and diary, kept by [Joseph] Nourse, with "Meditations and Reflections" beginning in 1792, and diary entries made irregularly, Feb. 22, 1812, until 1839 "last week in August", 1792-1839
    With notes of and thoughts on religion, generally entered on Sundays until October 17, 1828, when daily entries begin, containing comments on his life and public affairs. There is a list of his books made on August 23, 1836.
  - Letter and account book, kept by Joseph Nourse, 1822, 1832-1835
    Containing some letters written as register, Register's Office, Treasury Department, but chiefly personal letters and accounts, 1832-1835.
- LEGAL DOCUMENTS (Oversize)
  - Land deed, signed by Robert Carter, 1724; (photostatic copy)
  - Lease for a Year, 1805
  - Release and Confirmation, 1805